A Guide to the Papers of J. Rives Childs 1904-1967
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of J. Rives Childs 1904-1967
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9256-b
This collection consists of 19,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mr. Childs, Nice, France, on November 4, 1969.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Rives Childs was born in Lynchburg, Virginia, on February 6, 1893. He attended Virginia Military Institute (1909-1911), and received his B.A. from Randolph-Macon College in 1912. In 1915 he recieved a master's degree from Harvard. He served during the First World War in military intelligence and as liaison officer of radio intelligence with the French and British War offices. After the war, he worked in the Soviet Union with the A.R.A., and headed the relief operations in the Tartar Republic. Mr. Childs entered the U.S. Foreign Service in 1923, and was stationed during his long career primarily in the Middle East. Among his many posts were Ambassadorships to Saudi Arabia, Yemen, and Ethiopia. He is the author of numerous books and articles. Among his published works are The American Foreign Service, Casanoviana, Reliques of the Rives, Restif de la Bretonne: ses critiques et sa bibliographie, and a memoir, Foreign Service Farewell.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts for Child's books Behind the Scenes of History, Foreign Service Farewell, The Buried Life, Operation Torch, Satan's Redezvous, Casanoviana, and over 40 articles.
The foreign service materials include memoranda, correspondence, dispatches, speeches, pamphlets, invitations, scrapbooks, photographs, press releases, reports and documents for Rives's career in Saudi Arabia, Yemen, and Ethiopia. There are materials from Rives's service in military intelligence during the first world war, and with the American Relief Administration in the Tartar republic.
The papers also contain personal correspondence from 1904-1967, genealogical material, and travel diaries.
Contents List
- Behind the Scenes of History by J. Rives Childs n.d., TMs, pt. 1, 412 pp.; pt. 2, 407 p. (Box 1)
- Foreign Service Farewell: Thirty Years in the Near East by J. Rives Childs n.d., TMs, 298 pp. and 15 pages of footnotes (Box 2)
- Drafts of his autobiography--no title n.d., TMs, 470 pp. (Box 2)
- Account with Ambulance Service n.d., TMs, 16 pp. (Box 2)
- Satan's Rendezvous by J. Rives Childs n.d., TMs, 277 pp. (Box 3)
- The Buried Life by J. Rives Childs n.d., TMs, 221 pp. (Box 3)
- poems (no title) by J. Rives Childs n.d., TMs, 63 pp. (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1951-1963, 44 letters (Box 4)
- Confidential notes and dispatches 1941-45, 6 items (Box 4)
- Correspondence 1955-56, 6 items (Box 4)
  Publishers to Writers' Service
- Operation Torch: An object lesson in diplomacy by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 248 pp. (Box 4)
- Operation Torch: An object lesson in diplomacy by J.R.C. n.d., Photostated copy of TMs, 252 pp. (Box 4)
- Materials n.d. (Box 5)
  re Childs' writings
- Correspondence with publishers 1916-1927, 50 items (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous poetry, Typed, printed, and Ms., 13 items (Box 5)
- "Gastronomica Americana" by Henry Filmer [J.R.C.] n.d., TMs, 6 pp. (Box 5)
- "Some Historical Background of the Anglo-Italian Accord" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 22 pp. (Box 5)
- "What Woodrow Wilson means to me" n.d., TMs, 10 pp. (Box 5)
- "Pages of History from Irun to Barcelona" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 31 pp. (Box 5)
- no title n.d., TMs, 4 pp. (Box 5)
- "A Modest Proposal for Eliminating Depressions" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 6 pp. (Box 5)
- "Some Social Aspects of Government Economy" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 11 pp. (Box 5)
- Joke letter to Republican National Committee n.d., TMs, 2 pp. (Box 5)
- "The Regulations Say Nothing of Life" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 10 pp. (Box 5)
- "Film Letter from France" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 3 pp. (Box 5)
- "Coincidences" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 6 pp. (Box 5)
- "How the White House Correspondents Association Was Born" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 6 pp. (Box 5)
- "Woman as a Subject for Satire" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 37 pp. (Box 5)
- Unpublished Fiction by Childs
  - "Playing the Market" n.d., TMs, 10 pp. (Box 5)
  - "Game of Fortune" n.d., TMs, 7 pp. (Box 5)
  - no title n.d., TMs, 2 pp. (Box 5)
  - "Maje" n.d., TMsS, 38 pp. (Box 5)
  - "Maje" n.d., TMs, 28 pp. (Box 5)
  - "The Unkown Quantity" n.d., TMsS, 8 pp. (Box 5)
  - "Fuku" n.d., TMs, 32 pp. (Box 5)
  - prayer (no title) n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 5)
  - "To the Dead in France" n.d., TMs poem, 1 p. (Box 5)
  - short story (no title) n.d., AMs, 12 pp. (Box 5)
  - short story (no title) n.d., AMs, 4 pp. (Box 5)
  - "To a Woman" n.d., TMs, poem, 1 p. (Box 5)
  - anecdote (no title) n.d., TMs, 1 p. (Box 5)
  - "Pearl White" n.d., TMs, 4 pp. (Box 5)
  - "Failure" n.d., TMs, 6 pp. (Box 5)
  - no title n.d., AMs, 49 pp. (Box 5)
  - no title n.d., AMs, 21 pp. (Box 5)
- Printed Reviews of Escape to Cairo ca. 1938, 15 items (Box 5)
- Materials on Before the Curtain Falls (Box 5)
- Dust jacket of Before the Curtain Falls (Box 5)
- "Identity of Characters in Before the Curtain Falls" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 2 pp. (Box 5)
- writing on the front and back flap of dust jacket n.d., TMs, 2 pp., 2nd copy, 2 pp. (Box 5)
- Papers on Restif de la Bretonne, Typed, handwritten, and printed, 2 folders; 200 items (Box 6)
- Casanova
  - Contract on Casanova bibliography June 20, 1960, Printed contract, 3 pp. (Box 7)
  - Casanova: A Biography by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 431 pp. (Box 7)
  - The Ragged Edge by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 355 pp. (Box 7)
  - "The Iconography of Casanova's Memoirs" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 11 pp. (Box 8)
  - "Casanova et la Diplomatie" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 9 pp. (Box 8)
  - "Casanova and Diplomacy" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 14 pp. (Box 8)
  - "Dechiffrement d'une Oeurre anonyme de Jacques Casanova" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 14 pp. (Box 8)
  - Casanova[French translation] by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 422 pp. (Box 8)
  - Giacono Casanova de Seingalt by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 434 pp. (Box 8)
- Confidential Materials on Childs' Tangier Consulate
  - Childs to Secretary of State [Cordell Hull] November 17, 1943, TMs, 3 pp. (Box 9)
  - Memorandum on Br. policy April 18, 1944, TMs, 8 pp. (Box 9)
  - Childs to Henry H. Villard, Esq. January 10, 1945, TMs, 2 pp. (Box 9)
  - Letter and memorandum of J.R.C. to the Secretary of State [Edward Stettinius] February 10, 1945, TMs, 7 pp. (Box 9)
  - Memorandum of Morocco March 26, 1930, TMs, 28 pp. (Box 9)
  - "Notebook on North African areas, esp. Morocco" by J.R.C. December 16, 1940, TMs, 132 pp. (Box 9)
  - Materials from Tangier Consulate 1939-1945, 27 items (Box 9)
    including some correspondence and dispatches
  - Photographs of Morocco n.d., 29 items (Box 9)
- Palestine
  - "Morocco, Egypt and Palestine", a speech by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 52 pp. (Box 10)
  - Letters, memoranda, and articles 1925-1945, TMs & Printed, 24 items (Box 10)
    re Palestine
  - Notebook on Palestine ca. 1939, TMs, 143 pp. (Box 10)
- Near East
  - General Egyptian Information, Memoranda and Pamphlets, 3 items (Box 11)
  - Confidential Reports from Cairo ca. 1932 (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to the Secretary of State [Henry L. Stimson] December 10, 1932, TMs, 5 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] June 7, 1932, TMs, 5 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] June 1, 1932, TMs, 9 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] December 29, 1932, TMs, 10 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary State, [Henry L. Stimson] January 9, 1933, TMs, 12 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] February 19, 1932, TMs, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] March 16, 1932, TMs, 10 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Cordell Hull] April 13, 1932, TMs, 8 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] February 2, 1932, TMs, 4 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] January 14, 1932, TMs, 5 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] November 21, 1931, TMs, 5 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry L. Stimson] June 17, 1931, TMs, 6 pp. (Box 11)
  - J.R.C. to Secretary of State, [Cordell Hull] September 8, 1973, TMs, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - ________ to Secretary of State, [Cordell Hull] August 13, 1933, TMs, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to J.R.C. February 15, 1935, TMs, 14 pp. (Box 11)
  - W.M. Jardine to Secretary of State, [Henry Stimson] January 9, 1933, TMs, 10 pp. (Box 11)
- The Suez Canal
  - J.R.C. to Edwin C. Wilson March 31, 1938, TL, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - "A Selected Bibliography" on Egypt by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 13 pp. (Box 11)
  - News Bulletin April 1, 1938, Printed Bulletin, 15 pp. (Box 11)
  - Congressional Record June 13, 1938, Printed bulletin, 8 p. (Box 11)
  - "The Suez Canal and League Sanctions" by Raymond L. Buell August 27, 1935, Printed pamplet, 17 pp. (Box 11)
  - "The Suez Canal and The Outlook for Egypt" by Halford L. Hoskins February 1, 1944, Printed pamphlet, 10 pp. (Box 11)
  - J.R.C. to Mr. Wynne March 10, 1939, TLS, 1 p. & reply (Box 11)
  - "Italy and the Suez Canal" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 15 pp. (Box 11)
  - "The Suez Canal" by J.R.C. April 6, 1939, TMs, 13 pp. (Box 11)
- Egyptian Dispatches
  - Letters ca. 1930-1940, TL, 32 items (Box 11)
- Correspondence in Teheran
  - Letters & Memoranda ca. 1934, TMsS, 29 items (Box 11)
  - "Trans-Jordan: Borderland of History" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs (speech), 49 pp. (Box 11)
  - "Trans-Caspia" by J.R.C. 1938 or 1939, TMs (lecture), 46 pp. (Box 11)
  - "Iran" (speech) by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 21 pp. (Box 11)
  - no title (speech on Iran) n.d., TMs, 22 pp. (Box 11)
  - no title (speech on choosing a profession) by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - no title (speech on Palestine) by J.R.C. 1922, TMs, 55 pp. (three drafts, 2nd - 3 pp.; 34d - 4 pp.) (Box 11)
  - "Cooperation in the Field between the State and Defense Departments" (speech) by J.R.C. Jan. 4, 1951, TMs, 19 pp. (Box 11)
  - excerpts from speech "Coordinator of the Political and Military Branches of Government" n.d., TMs, 7 pp. (Box 11)
  - no title (Memorial Day Speech) by J.R.C. n.d., AMs, 3 pp. (Box 11)
- Near Eastern Materials
  - Ethiopia
    - "Travel to the Blue Nile" by J.R.C. November 20, 1952, TMs, 3 pp. (Box 12)
    - "New United States Ambassador to Ethiopia presents Credentials.. ." May 19, 1951, Printed article, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie September 6, 1951, AMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie March 14, 1950, AMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie October 7, 1952, AMs, 1 p. (Box 13)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie May 29, 1951, AMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie June 13, 1951, AMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Imperial Invitation to dinner from Haile Sellassie November 3, 1951, AMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - Ethiopian Visa, Printed visa, 1 p. (Box 12)
  - Turkey
    - "Turkey's International Political Committments" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 44 pp. (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on the Middle East
    - "When the Golden Rule Came to Jerusalem" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs (Box 12)
    - "Cairo to Teheran by Automobile" March 24, 1934, TMs, 14 pp. (Box 12)
    - "H.I.M. Reza Shah Pahlavi" n.d., TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - Travel itinerary n.d., TMs, 5 pp. (Box 12)
    - Teheran n.d., Printed pamphlet, 7 pp. (Box 12)
  - Ambassadorship in Saudi Arabia
    - no title (article on Jidda) n.d., TMs, 12 pp. (Box 12)
    - Diplomatic List, Jidda, Saudi Arabia Jan. 15, 1948, TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - Diplomatic and Resident Foreigners, Jidda February 10, 1947, TMs, 4 pp. (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on King Ibn Saud
    - Yousuf Yassin to Mr. Childs Jan. 23, 1950, TL, 1 p. with translation (Box 12)
    - Press release on Ibn Saud Jan. 27, [19__], TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - Press release on a feast of Ibn Saud Jan. 23, [19__], TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - Press release on Ibn Saud's visit to an American Oil Refinery Jan. 22, [19__), TMs, 5 pp. (Box 12)
    - "The New Reign in Saudi Arabia" by J.B. Philby April 1954, TMs, 11 pp. [copied from vol. 32, no. 3 of Foreign Affairs] (Box 12)
    - "Arabian Sun and Flares: Life of Ibn Saud" n.d., TMs, 8 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Au banquet de petrole, Ibn Seoud menge, seul, un chameau de lait" February 25, 1947, Printed article and picture, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Des Marchenkonig aus dem Morgenland" March 26, 1969, Printed article and pictures, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Our Strangest Ally" by C.L. Sulzberger May 10, 1947, Printed article and picture, 3 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Deux Rois des Mille et une Nuits" June 25, 1952, Printed article and pictures, 3 pp. (Box 12)
  - Visit of Amir Saud to the United States
    - "Princeton University Visited by Amir Saud" Jan. 23, [19__], TMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - "Prince Saud Visits U.N. Headquarters" Jan. 22, [19__], TMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
    - "Amir Saud sees Texas Refinery" Jan. 27, [19__], TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Amir Saud takes the Controls of a Constellation" Jan. 25, [19__], TMs, 1 p. (Box 12)
  - Saudi Arabia (general)
    - "Reconnaissance in Saudi Arabia" n.d., Printed article, 12 pp. (Box 12)
    - "Guest in Saudi Arabia" by Maynard Owen Williams n.d., Printed article, 27, pp. (Box 12)
  - General Materials on the Near East
    - Memorandum on Lawrence of Arabia Jan. 10, 1939, TMs, 3 pp. (Box 12)
    - Memorandum on Moral Authority of the Arab Rebels Jan. 10, 1939, TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - Memorandum on Syrian Minister to France Jan. 12, 1939, TMs, 2 pp. (Box 12)
    - no title (article on Near East) n.d., TMs, 13 pp. (Box 12)
    - J.R.C. to Henry A. Byroade Dec. 18, 1952, TMs, 4 pp. (Box 12)
    - La France et l'Iran by Jean Pozzi Jan. 1, 1937, Printed pamphlet, 22 pp. (Box 12)
    - Persian Painting 1552 A.D., Print, 1 p. (Box 12)
  - Thirty Years in the Near East by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 235 pp. (Box 12)
- Childs and the Foreign Service
  - "Let's Stop Reforming the Foreign Service" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 7 pp., 2 drafts (Box 13)
  - "For Sale: The American Foreign Service" by Henry Filmer [J.R.C.] n.d., TMs, 14 pp. (Box 13)
- Notices of Diplomatic Appointments
  - Notice of appointment to Yemen August 22, 1946, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of promotion to position of Career Minister Feb. 3, 1947, 2 pp. (Box 13)
  - Notice of appointment to post at Saudi Arabia March 2, 1949, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of appointment to kingdom of Yemen January 13, 1947, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of appointment as Consul of Gilbraltar October 28, 1942, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of appointment to Ethiopia April 19, 1951 (Box 13)
  - Acceptance of Childs by George VI, signed by Anthony Eden Feb. 10, 1942, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of Childs' appointment of Consul General to Tangier May 8, 1942, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Notice of promotion of Childs to class two August 12, 1944, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Manuscript, in Arabic (Box 13)
- A Boy's Story of the Foreign Service n.d., TMs, 215 pp. (Box 13)
- Letters
  re: Ethiopian Appointment
  - From American Embassy to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in the Imperial Ethiopian Government February 26, 1951, TMs (Box 13)
  - Acheson to American Embassy at Addis Ababa Feb. 21, 1951, TL, 1 p. (Box 13)
- Correspondence
  re: Childs Resignation from the Foreign Service
  - Bruce Acting to American Diplomatic Officers November 10, 1952, TL, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - J.R.C. to Presidential Appointments Staff November 14, 1952, TL, 2 pp. (Box 13)
  - J.R.C. to Mr. President Nov. 14, 1952, TL, 1 p. (Box 13)
  - Robert [Bob] F. Woodward to Rives September 15, 1952, TLS, 1 p. (Box 13)
- Memorandum for Improving the Foreign Service
  - "Suggestion for Improving the Foreign Service and its Administration.. ." by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 13 pp. (3 drafts) (Box 13)
  - no title November 14, 1944, AMS, 1 p. (Box 13)
    re languages and the Foreign Service
- "The American Foreign Service" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 226 pp. (Box 13)
- "Foreign Service Farewell: My Years in the Middle East" n.d., Printed draft, 184 pp. (Box 13)
- Childs' correspondence, 18 items (Box 13)
  re Foreign Service
- Cyphers and Cryptography
  - Materials on German Cyphers and Codes
    - "German Codes and Ciphers" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 10 pp. (Box 14)
    - "The War Against German Ciphers" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 38 pp., 2 drafts (Box 14)
    - German Military Ciphers November 1918, TMs, 75 pp. (Box 14)
    - ________ to Rives April 1961, TL, 2 pp. (Box 14)
    - Data for the Solution of German Ciphers 1917, Printed pamphlet, 2 pp. (Box 14)
    - "Transposition Ciphers used by the Germans" November 29, 1918, TMs, 1 p. (Box 14)
    - Friedmann to J.R.C. Dec. 9, 1959, ALS, 4 pp. (Box 14)
    - "War Intercepts" by David Kahn n.d., TMs, 78 pp. (Box 14)
    - "Two Americans" by David Kahn n.d., TMs, 89 pp. (Box 14)
    - "The History and Principles of German military ciphers" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 212 pp. (Box 14)
- Materials on the Russian Famine
  - "Red Days in Russia" by J.R.C. n.d., TMs, 384 pp. (Box 15)
  - American Relief Administration Bulletin January 1922, Mimegraphed bulletin, 39 pp. (Box 15)
  - American Relief Administration Bulletin January 1923, Mimeographed bulletin, 86 pp. (Box 15)
  - American Relief Administration Association Review January 1944, Printed magazine, 35 pp. (Box 15)
  - American Relief Administration 1919, Printed magazine, 20 pp. (Box 15)
  - Materials and impressions of the Russian Famine, 40 items (Box 15)
  - Childs' Russian Diary 1921-1923, TMs, 209 pp. (Box 15)
- Russian Famine
  - Childs' miscellaneous Russian papers, 31 large items (Box 16)
  - Congratulatory letters 1922-23, TMs, 10 items (Box 16)
    re: ARA
  - Scrapbook on the Russian Famine n.d., 96 pp. (Box 16)
- Russian Documents
  - "Persia and the Soviet Union, 1917-1934" by J. Rives Childs November 26, 1934, TMs, 373 pp. (Box 17)
  - "Documents re: relations between Persia and Russia, 1828-1931" n.d., TMs, 257 pp. (Box 17)
  - "Report on the Central Volga Region" by J.R.C. August 7, 1926, TMs, 152 pp. (Box 17)
  - The Evacuation of North Russia, 1919 1920, Published documents, 45 pp. & maps (Box 17)
  - A. Nibin to Childs April 7, 1923, ALS, 3 pp. (Box 17)
  - A. Flyne to Madam [Mrs. Childs] Nov. 2, [19__], ALS, 4 pp. (Box 17)
- Russia
  - Miscellaneous articles and letters, 20 items (Box 18)
    re Soviet Russia
  - Articles on Russia in the 1920s ca. 1920-1930, TMs, 10 items (Box 18)
  - Mrs. Hallie Ermine Childs n.d., Photograph (Box 18)
  - Russian Currency, 66 pieces (Box 18)
  - Photographs of the Russian Famine ca. 1922, 73 items (Box 18)
  - Published articles ca. 1922, 7 items (Box 18)
    re the Russian Famine
- Personal Correspondence with Family 1904-1915
  - Correspondence 1904, 2 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1908, 1 item (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1909, 39 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1910, 44 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1911, 25 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1912, 3 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1913, 28 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1914, 3 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1915, 12 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1914-15, 52 items (Box 19)
- Correspondence to Parents 1916-1925
  - Correspondence 1916, 4 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1917, 5 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1918, 16 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1919, 31 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1920, 45 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1921, 67 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1922 (Box 46 items)
  - Correspondence 1923, 11 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1924, 47 items (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1925, 15 items (Box 20)
- Correspondence to Parents 1926-1945
  - Correspondence 1926, 20 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1927, 30 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1928, 34 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1929, 44 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1930, 20 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1931, 44 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1932, 23 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1933, 29 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1934, 21 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1935, 25 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1935, 25 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1936, 19 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1937, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1938, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1939, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1939, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1940, 1 item (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1941, 22 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1942, 27 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1943, 31 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1944, 27 items (Box 21)
  - Correspondence 1945, 15 items (Box 21)
- Correspondence to Parents n.d., 139 items (Box 22)
- Personal Correspondence
  - Letters ca. 1947, ALS, 3 items (Box 23)
    re: Childs' mother's death
  - Correspondence 1952-53, 21 items (Box 23)
    re: Childs' writings
  - Correspondence with Alfred Dennis 1915-1918, 16 items (Box 23)
  - Correspondence 1964-1965, 129 items (Box 23)
    re: Mrs. G. Childs' death
  - Correspondence 1952, 7 items (Box 23)
    re: the death of Mms. de Brylkine
- Personal Correspondence (non-family) 1916-1953
  - Correspondence 1916-1930, 43 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1930-1933, 44 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1934, 27 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1935, 17 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1936, 14 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1937, 29 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1938, 19 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1939, 11 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1940, 12 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1941, 3 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1942, 2 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1943, 5 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1944, 13 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1945, 23 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1946, 9 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence s 1947, 9 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1948, 17 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1949, 11 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1950, 34 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1951, 30 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1952, 36 items (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1953, 114 items (Box 24)
- Correspondence to and from Friends (topics)
  - re: Lawrenceville School ca. 1915, ALS & printed materials; 24 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1912, 2 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1913, 5 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1914, 4 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1915, 2 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1916, 10 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1917, 23 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1918, 5 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1919, 19 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1920, 17 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence 1921, 6 items (Box 25)
  - Correspondence n.d., 30 items (Box 25)
- Correspondence (general) 1954-1958
  - Correspondence 1954, 117 items (Box 26)
  - Correspondence 1955, 83 items (Box 26)
  - Correspondence 1956, 64 items (Box 26)
  - Correspondence 1957, 11 items (Box 26)
  - Correspondence 1958, 43 items (Box 26)
- Correspondence (general) 1959-1965
  - Correspondence 1959, 42 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1960, 65 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1961, 69 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1962, 105 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1963, 107 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1964, 47 items (Box 27)
  - Correspondence 1965, 98 items (Box 27)
- Correspondence (general) 1965-1967
  - Correspondence 1965, 79 items (Box 28)
  - Correspondence 1965, 65 items (Box 28)
  - Correspondence 1966, 72 items (Box 28)
  - Correspondence 1967, 73 items (Box 28)
  - Correspondence 1967, 50 items (Box 28)
- Casanova Correspondence 1952-1958
  - Correspondence 1952, 34 items (Box 29)
  - Correspondence 1953, 9 items (Box 29)
  - Correspondence 1954, 72 items (Box 29)